hello and welcome everyone this is
active lab guest stream number 22.1
i'm here with dr anna lumke and we are
here to discuss
dopamine and beyond and
really looking forward to this
conversation and appreciate the time so
to you for
any introductory context and then really
looking forward to this discussion
yeah well thank you so much for having
me daniel you know i've uh
been uh you know interested in you and
your work for many years now and so i'm
really excited to have
an excuse to reconnect
um and just excited to be here and you
asked me to start by introducing myself
so i'm i'm a professor of psychiatry and
behavioral sciences and also addiction
medicine
at lanford university school of medicine
i'm also author of the book dopamine
nation finding balance in the age of
indulgence and that's what we're going
to talk about which i and daniel's
quoted in there and i would have
actually included daniel moore in there
if i had if i were smart enough to
actually understand the work that he
does
thanks um
we'll get there with the ants and the
dopamine but yeah just what is dopamine
nation about and what motivated you to
write it
so dopamination is kind of a blend of
neuroscience made simple
combined with
practical advice for how to live in a
dopamine overloaded world
holding up people in recovery from
severe addictions as modern day profits
for the rest of us because all the
neuroscience in the world as valuable as
it is
um can't make up for the whole
experience of people who have gotten
into recovery from addiction
um dopamine nation also
posits a kind of global hypothesis you
know tentatively posits the hypothesis
that the growing rates of anxiety
depression suicide and other mental
health disorders across the world
are caused at least in part
by the problem of overabundance uh and
the kind of lack of appropriate friction
in our lives in other words the ways in
which our lives are maybe too easy and
the way that our primitive wiring is
mismatched for this modern ecosystem of
overwhelming over abundance
okay
one dopamine question and then i think
we'll start to see some areas of overlap
with active inference
what could you say to the role of
dopamine in reward and motivation
signaling like in wanting and liking and
how does dopamine play a role
in behavioral selection
okay so dopamine is essential for the
experience of motivation reward and
pleasure
it may be even more important for
motivation than it is uh for the
experience of pleasure and i base this
on the work of my amazing neuroscience
colleagues who have done experiments for
example where they engineer a rat's
brain to do completed dopamine receptors
and discover that if they give that rat
food it will eat the food and seem to
take pleasure in the food but if they
put the food you know some distance away
the rat will starve to death meaning
that the absence of dopamine in these
key reward circuits
um make it such that that animal is no
longer
motivated to do the work that it takes
uh to get their reward and
my neuroscience colleagues like rob
malenka
had said that for him the definition of
addiction is how hard an animal is
willing to work to get their reward
and that has direct application to the
clinical work that i do
um you know we all like what we like and
once we experience the thing that we
like of course we want to repeat it but
the kind of fundamental
difference between those who go on to
develop addiction and those who don't is
that those who develop addiction are
willing to work very very hard to get
their drug of choice and are willing to
give up a lot of other things
even when that pursuit causes enormous
amount of
you know personal costs
thank you for that that's really
powerful with professor malenka's
definition of how hard they work to get
it because it's like an action-oriented
definition that could be measured in or
proxied by different things especially
clinically as opposed to like in
inference or a purely cognitive based
report like a survey how often do you
think about something like that
and uh that's very interesting and
that's i think one of the themes that
we'll pick up on which is
action and for active inference it's
right there in the title it's like
there's always going to be a minimum of
two and when we're talking about
behavior and cognition they're an
inseparable whole and then that plays
out in a lot of different ways like
partially with the embodiment and the
inactive perspectives that come to view
but also just like as you said it's
pragmatic too because it's relevant to
always be thinking about
action and cognition as like a dyad in
the context rather than trying to
separate them and then find a
correlation across
love it love it so
i've been a psychiatrist for
uh going on 30 25 years
and i would say the first half of my
training and
life experience and education was really
focused on changing people's cognitions
so focusing on people's thoughts and
emotions and using language as a tool to
talk about those to change those but as
my career went on i became more and more
skeptical of this as a solitary pursuit
and more and more convinced that what we
need to do is focus on changing behavior
and when i'm dealing with patients with
addiction that is in fact now my first
intervention
i will say let us first change the
behavior
and in doing that experiment and what i
mean is abstain from your drug of choice
see what happens and then let's make
certain inferences based on what that
experience was like for you and that's
really a typical in psychiatry today
what we do instead is we talk and we
talk and we talk about why the behaviors
are happening without really focusing on
changing the behaviors and i think we
really that that's not good like because
for example my patients will come in
they'll be addicted and they'll say i'm
addicted because i'm depressed or
because i have this trauma all of that
may be true
but we can talk about the trauma till
the cows come home you have to change
the behavior and you have to do it
before you feel like it so that's really
interesting too like patients will say
well
you know i'm just not i don't i'm not
motivated to do x y or z so this is an
earlier like i don't feel i said you
know what if you wait
till you feel like doing it you will
never do it what you need to do is
change the behavior
experience the impact on your
feeling by changing the behavior and
then take it from there
so i totally agree with you it's this
intense marriage of cognition emotion
and the actual actions and we almost
always are focused on you know the
cognitions and emotions
and we don't get people to do enough of
just focusing on changing behavior
okay so i think that's our first theme
which is this action orientation and
that plays into the embodiment and the
inactive aspects but also it has a kind
of corollary this like act first
principle
and that helps us perturb the causal
structure because if you're just looking
at the n equals one
observational experiment
well your consumption will be correlated
with
the price of oranges and then how do you
actually get at something deeper in the
world and that's sort of a relevant type
of intervention so action and also
action first is pretty
cool any other thoughts on that or we
can go in a different direction
well i would also say that this brings
to mind you know you asked about surveys
and things like that like i don't really
like
just personally like i don't really i
mean i think there's value for for like
survey studies but the problem is what
you really end up picking up there is
more about what the dominant cultural
narrative is that explains why people do
x y or z and you're not really tapping
into why they really do x y or z the
other thing i would say that you know
the way that we think about science is
that it's not
a single person's
life narrative but i really believe that
that that there's science when you
see a series of individuals over and
over again you hear their stories and
you can recognize very similar patterns
and then you do an intervention and you
see the results and you do that
repeatedly with many people over time
it's not like your classic you know a
clinical study but it feels really true
and real to me in a way that a lot of
times clinical studies don't or can't
capture some of the deeply nuanced
complex aspects of human behavior
i love the way you think about things
it's so crazy
now you're like
okay
i didn't know what was gonna
come next so um yeah
um all right so back to the book and
also to connect this to an active
inference theme so if decision making in
active inference like policy selection
the pi variable
the way that different possibilities are
ranked is not just by their reward or
their expected like value or utility
which would be common in a kind of
reinforcement learning or a reward
maximization framework but there's like
two components that go into that policy
selection there's a
epistemic knowledge oriented like
learning and curiosity intrinsic
motivation and then there's a pragmatic
so there is a utility element and the
ability to dial in on utility but also
there's the ability to kind of pull back
and when you were describing
your
book structure
certainly while reading it and as you
described it there was like an epistemic
component
neuroscience made accessible for those
who might not have the molecular
background but also like on page 48 with
a baseball game it's just fun for even
those who might have seen it in a
different
way and then there's the pragmatic part
which uses the stories um to kind of
connect
to useful tips so
where do you think epistemic and
pragmatic
value come into play in how you're
thinking about this
um
so
so epidemic is interesting um
and thank you for showing the examples
related to my book um because that helps
me also understand what you mean by
those terms
so what i find really interesting um
about
um
you know how to intrinsically motivate
people
with addiction
is that if they have a framework in
which to understand their behavior
it really does help people change their
behavior
it's really a framework and what's
fascinating to me is that neuroscience
talks and everything else walks
and by that i mean when i explain people
their behavior with a neuroscience
framework it carries a lot of currency
to people for people it feels real you
know it feels like it's almost like let
me just throw it out there like a modern
day religion like you could you could
use
a very different framework like you
could use a moral framework you could
use a philosophical framework
people don't resonate with that the same
way they resonate with the neuroscience
which is why i use the neuroscience
framework um so i think and
people will carry it around with them so
for example i use this extended metaphor
of a balance pleasure pain balance and
gremlins represent neuro adaptation and
they hop on the pain side of balance and
for example i had a reader write me and
say you know i'm trying really trying
really hard to quit smoking and whenever
i have an urge
to smoke a cigarette i just imagine
those little gremlins that was slowing
their adaptation hopping up and down in
the painting south i'm not you're not
gonna win you know i'm going to outlast
you um so that's really interesting
people will you know it's like a frame
we need those
epistemological frameworks that we
project onto the world to help us cope
make decisions
last you know in difficult situations
nice thanks um maybe even one way that
that person is experiencing their
um
experience the way that they're thinking
about their behavior and inference
it's um like
the the metaphor
that you're bringing the baseball game
the for the neurotransmitter synapse the
gremlins
even some of the more flow charts like
how different stages are related to each
other there's always like a person's
form
moving through it
and then that provides a lot of
accessibility
to enter into that space and like kind
of imagine counter factuals
which is our
human cognitive
expertise in a sense is not to memorize
11 digit numbers even
outside of ultra specific training it's
to
like
okay if the neurotransmitter like when i
looked at that example i thought well
where are the glia are they the crowd
are they like
what are they doing are they supporting
this pitch
and then there's that time scale but
then it already opens the door to
questions that the molecular
representation's like oh well then it's
a done deal right with the pre the post
synaptic
yeah right and i think
you know
um
obviously these metaphors are like a
gross oversimplification and get things
you know can't explain all of the
phenomena but as you say if we try to
explain it all and we get too
complicated then it feels to people like
memorizing a list of numbers so it has
to be true enough to represent the real
science but not so complex that people
can't take it with them and apply it in
their everyday everyday lives
and it also it takes it out of the the
kind of uncanny valley
an example there would be like the
ribosome it's a purple blob
and right well it's really not but it's
represented so commonly
and then that locks in but then at the
baseball game we know it's not it's a
different scale
so it's approachable and then anyone who
wants to look into the receptor slash
glove
yes yeah so um
okay
um that was kind of exploring
what was the second area which was like
the epistemic and the pragmatic like
always pairing
the knowledge gaining with the useful
and then recognizing that there's a time
for the more knowledge oriented maybe
there's a building on campus that's more
knowledge oriented and then also there's
a time and a place for what's useful
and maybe that's part of the
conversation that
do you want to see or how do you want to
see it with applied neuroscience
um
can you can you say what you mean a
little bit more i didn't quite get that
like connecting the epistemic and the
pragmatic the learning and research
oriented work
with the practical
tips
is that disconnect how could it be how
should it be how will we make that
connection like flexible and and work
yeah i mean there's obviously you know a
huge disconnect like this is this is the
problem we're sort of you know in this
ivory tower we're we're learning this
stuff we're acquiring this knowledge
we're working you know people you know
neuroscientists like you actually
adding new knowledge but yeah then the
question is how do we get that to people
to actually you know benefit them
um you know in their everyday lives and
also get it getting it to to students to
give them a sense of meaning and purpose
in their work so it doesn't feel so
incredibly disembodied from the world
that we live in
and the reasons behind
why we do i mean why do we want to
acquire this knowledge i mean you know
there's there's not just that i mean
maybe it is knowledge for its own sake
but i think deeply people want to feel
they're contributing making the world a
better place uh you know so i think
really important to to do we need to do
more to bring those things
together
um
i feel like you know
medical education
the so there's the pre-clinical years
and then there's the clinical years and
i know for me personally
like those clinical years were where i
first sort of felt like oh thank
goodness you know here i am interacting
with like real human beings and trying
to take this knowledge
and also i'm impatient i'm very
impatient so i feel like the human
interaction i could see more quickly
that i was making a difference i didn't
have the kind of patience that it takes
to be a scientist
in the sense that you are where you
really have to
have a deep deep faith that what you're
doing matters and that down the road you
will see it's you know it's it's
application
um unless you unless it's just the
beauty of it
you know for its own sake compels you
and draws you in but i'm ultimately a
very kind of pragmatic person and so i
and i'm also impatient so i need to see
that a lot a lot sooner but how about
you i'm sure you have many thoughts on
this i'd love to hear them
well yes very
interesting and as we were kind of
joking about before like
everyone especially in an age of
specialization abundance of specialisms
that being able to like connect across
them is really important like
having not had first-hand experience in
for example any of the
stories presented
and that's like the microcosm of the
discussion with
frameworks and
people's lives kind of meeting from the
ground up so
patience
that's an interesting thing and you
point into like how different people
seemingly display behaviorally different
amounts of patience and they probably
experience it differently too but also
it's patience for different things
right intermittent fasting over this
many hours or this many days
all the things might align for one
person at one time and it very
easy to be patient behaviorally versus
not versus some other strategy
and so trying to think about that in an
active inference way it's like in active
inference the question is always about
what is the decision
right now
or inference and action so how should i
be perceiving and learning
and acting in the moment
given
the long horizon or the the stated
horizon so
what is going to be the best move
in this chess move
given the kind of uncertainty about the
future of the game include including
like the uncertainty about what the
other side will do or something like
that or even uncertainty over one's own
actions
and then patience is like well
what
is happening when the best action
selection
is to
not engage with something
so what is it that actually
values
for something that is valuable like it's
easy to be patient for something that's
just a purely negative experience right
i'll just i'll hold off not interested
but being patient we kind of are
applying to something where it's like
i do want to
call this person before the time i said
i would call them but i'm getting
impatient or like i want this research
project to be over i wish that this was
faster which everyone involved in
research or maybe analogously like it
would be awesome if myself or if this
patients were
seemingly on their recovery
faster or something
so
how does it come to be that sometimes
we wait in the moment
and other other times we don't
and like is it okay or when should we do
stuff
yeah
um
gosh so much there
so let's start with your question how
how does it come to be how how do we i
mean
you know
i quote you in the book saying that the
world is uh century rich and causal poor
and i i just love that quote because it
wraps up in this night nice little
package
um
the the
the problem with highly reinforcing
drugs and behaviors
which is that in the moment they feel
like the right thing and they feel good
but the long-term consequences of
repeated use is to get us to a
potentially very dark place
but we don't necessarily see the
connection between those two things
right so how is it that we come to see
that connection
and i think as a psychiatrist having
listened to thousands and thousands of
people's narrative life stories over
time that one of the ways that we get
there is actually the autobiographical
self narrative
that that that words are tools
and that those tools are a way not just
to organize past experience but actually
create road maps for the future
so it's not just
um you know
the the way that we tell our stories
about our lives
are very very impactful i think puko or
somebody like that said said that that
autobiographical narrative is the only
way that we have to document live time
which is really really interesting like
for all of the cool technology that we
have the only thing that documents live
time is
storytelling so and i've seen this again
and again when my patients come in and
they tell an autobiographical narrative
in which they are constantly the victim
of the world and other people and that's
why they're addicted
those people are not going to get better
and part of what i need to do over time
is to move them toward what i consider
to be a more truthful narrative which is
that there's always something that we
have contributed to the problem you know
maybe we just showed up and that was our
contribution but it's never
always entirely somebody else's fault
and for people who get into a sustained
and robust recovery
you can hear the difference in their
autobiographical narratives and one of
the fundamental differences they're able
to tolerate the shame
that comes with acknowledging their
character defects and the mistakes that
they made and what they contributed to
their messed up situation which is just
basically closer to the truth so telling
the truth is really important telling
truthful stories is really important and
i think that those stories actually
become the tool by which
we are able to
remain patient in the face of you know
delayed gratification
that's what keeps us able to
not to do something that we should do in
the moment but don't feel like doing or
to abstain from doing something that we
feel like doing in the moment but
shouldn't do
um and you know whether that story takes
a framework based on neuroscience or
whether there's a religious or spiritual
framework like
um you know my reward will come in
another life
there are many different ways to you
know build that story uh but that story
has got to be the thing that allows that
person to kind of you know delay this
gratification in the service of
um you know
living a more flourishing life
i'd like to ask a follow-up question
from the chat and then give a remark
neuropixel nice screen name asks
how can we learn to build patients for
healthy habits
okay how can we learn to build that's so
so good so i think there are a couple uh
there are a couple
stages
first um
it's to recognize that when you first
stop doing
a bad habit
you will suffer more so that the initial
your initial experience will be
increased pain
not
like immediate reward from stopping that
bad habit so i think so that like
setting up expectations in that way but
that the longer you can go abstaining
from that bad habit
the the faster you will get to that
place
where you
begin to feel better and you don't miss
that bad habit in fact you you start to
reap the benefits remember you have to
know it's going to get worse before it
gets better
everybody talks about practicing
mindfulness and what that is but
actually there's almost no better
opportunity for practicing mindfulness
than to give up something that's bad for
you that you really like a bad habit
because what will happen is it'll stir
up all kinds it's very disruptive
and i think then the ability to learn
that you are not your thoughts and
emotions but that you can stand some
distance from that and not
respond to that but just objectively
observe those things
is is really important
um
i think
do it giving up a bad hat bad habit with
other people so that you're not doing it
alone is really important um because you
can then you know go to other people and
and sort of suffer together
and then i think meaning making is
really important so to give up the bad
habit so that you yourself can feel
better but also what is the
what is the greater meaning
of abstaining uh from that thing and
often it's a consumpting process and you
know a greater meeting could be saving
the planet right i'm doing this for me
but it's also good for the world
thanks for the answer so yeah
one of those words you mentioned was
expectations
which is a core idea in
bayesian statistics and a long history
of like bayesian brain predictive coding
predictive processing many different
approaches to
neuroscience behavior and so on and
active inference does build on that and
uses the idea of expectations
as far as expected futures and things
like that a lot and so it's interesting
to think about the role of dopamine and
like you said set up for this because
then it'll basically go that way and
you'll stay on track whereas if you
expect to go faster or different you're
going to feel like worse or anxious or
uncertain about how to proceed and it's
totally modeled in an active inference
way
by thinking about like the estimate is
not how many points how many are am i
getting it's how many points relative to
how many points i expect
and then one can be doing better or
worse or as expected
and if things are going well there's
positive valence if things are going as
expected it's like neutral valence and
then things are going poor there's like
anxiety and negative valence right and
so that is one way where
moving from like a reward only
perspective to be like well yes there's
an expectation of reward and precision
along that path
will be pleasurable or neutral but it's
not going to be like winning winning
winning it'll be like neutral with
oscillation around neutral
right
yeah and i can tell you you know in the
like the lived experience of treating
patients this is absolutely key so one
of the things that we do in our clinic
um is to help people
get off of chronic opioids like you know
oxycontin or vicodin or norco or chronic
benzodiazepines like xanax
thallium atom
and
you know
you would think this is not that
complicated but actually
a lot of patients are looking for help
with this and can't find it and they
find it in our clinic and the one thing
that i would say we provide
which is the real value is to
establish appropriate expectations
because what happens is they'll go see a
doctor and they'll say i need to get off
a xanax or i really want to get off the
xanax and the doctor says oh that's easy
you know just go down by you know
uh you know 50 of your starting dose
over the next week and you'll be fine
and the patients
do that or same thing with their opioid
they do that and they're in horrific
psychological and physical pain because
they're in withdrawal or maybe they even
have a seizure right
so
their experience is totally worse or
much worse than what their doctor
predicted for the doctor is like the
respected authority so then they feel
angry they also feel betrayed they also
feel like they're weird like why why am
i they come to us and my patients have
told me again and again doctor argue the
most important thing you said to me when
we went down by my opioid or my benzo by
a little bit and we go very slowly
is that i would feel worse before i feel
better
and i really do i way emphasize that so
that if they go and they taper and it's
not even
it's not as bad as what i then they're
like happy it's like you know you told
me it was going to be bad for a while
until my body really recruited it
re-equilibrated and it was bad but it
wasn't like i could do it you know so
that setting expectations it's really
really important like in the real world
it's almost like there's a wanting
for
reduction or sobriety
but actually they don't like it
behaviorally not on the psychological
what are they thinking what does the
survey say
but actually like well you don't like
the green room if you aren't spending
your time in it it's how we would say it
about the other kinds of
animals so it's kind of like interesting
like where do we like something but not
want it what is dopamine and other
neurotransmitters doing then how about
the situations where we do or don't
have patience like those are such great
questions and entry points for our own
life and for
research and that's like kind of the
bridge is
the introduction of the paper or the
context for the grant is like kind of
could be
that bridge but then sometimes it
is more about how it appears rather than
how it is
yeah and i think the variable of time is
so important um for all of these things
like if i mean you know we can sign up
for a lot of suffering if you know it's
time limited right like okay i can do
this because dr lemke said i would feel
like crap for two weeks and i would
start to feel better and so you know you
can hang in there for that or or
whatever you know the the intervention
is that that makes a huge difference
so
returning to
the
quote on
page 75
about uh the world is sensory rich and
causal poor you know
personal communication uh
when 2018 because i think there's a very
interesting difference or something and
how i'm thinking about it now
oh interesting okay i'd love to hear
that
so i think that was
when i was just beginning to learn about
active inference and free energy
principle and bayesian brain and i was
thinking well wow it's not just like
signal detection on
the pixels or whatever
there's the causal inference and then
that's like you followed up like we know
the donut tastes good in the moment but
we are less aware that eating a donut
every day for a month adds five pounds
to our waistline
we get that understanding through
personal experience
relationships
science research
we build that understanding that
expectation of cause in and then all of
a sudden our behavior is like more
natural to switch in the moment so
i was thinking you know starry eyed
graduate student
sensory rich in causal poor i think now
i might say
sensory poor and causal poor
because
the sensory part
is
of extremely limited
frequency only some chemicals that we
can detect only some sounds that we hear
even within a domain
we're not always paying attention
our blind spot is evidence that we're in
a generative model of vision because the
sensory data is sparse and noisy and
blurry
and so it's like in the world that
sensory poor and causal poor
we can finally disengage from this like
watching a movie
perspective and it's like it's so
generative it's so much about our
expectations of the cause and also we're
not just watching a movie a vision and
we're expecting expecting and generating
even that
yeah so powerful i think this is really
why i i think there's so much power in
our self-narratives
because i think those self-narratives
that we project onto the world
absolutely impact
what we perceive
i just yesterday i was meeting with a
very beloved uh patient of mine
who happens to be you know a a
a a graduate student
um you know who has had a really
mixed experience in his lab
and feels like
he hasn't many friends and nobody likes
him
and
also feels like um
like they're all jerks and they're kind
of out to get him
and what i tried to get him to see
is that
he has a narrative and a vision that he
superimposes on the world such that all
he remembers or appreciates is like the
slights right and he doesn't he doesn't
have access to the other things because
he's so entrenched
in this particular version of the world
um
just to give like a personal example
um you know i talk about in the book my
comp very complicated relationship with
my mom
and how part of the healing for my
relationship was to get out of this
place where i'm always saying how how
terrible she is
and instead appreciating really the
great things about her which are many
and also you know what i've contributed
to the problem but before i could do
that
i was engaging in behaviors that just
reinforced my worldview and i'll give
you a very tangible example um
you know
one of the things that that you know had
bothered me about her was that i would
email her and she wouldn't respond to my
email in a timely or what i felt was
appropriate fashion
and this came up at one point where i
emailed about her about something that
was really important i felt it was
really important and she didn't respond
and i gave her a week and then i gave
her a month and i gave her three months
and i got angrier and angrier as time
went on and you know railed about it to
my husband say see this is exactly what
i'm talking about
and then you know i was eventually just
able to just forget about it and
whatever move on
and then i was on email and kind of
looking through i don't know kind of
cleaning up my email and discovered that
my original email that i had sent to her
that i was so angry that she hadn't
responded to was actually in my draft
box it had never been sent
and i think there are so many ways in
which we do that where where we don't
even get the opportunity to see it like
it was just in this case i did but we we
sort of do these things to sort of you
know hold on to this world new which
typically has other people being the bad
actors and it doesn't force us to look
at ourselves
thanks so
one
interesting piece there is like
we might be totally on board for
the past being a reconstruction in the
present the generative aspect of memory
and then it's also easy to believe in
the generative aspect of the future it
hasn't happened yet we don't know about
it and then
as per that predictive coding type of
like sensory generative model
we're also now casting so it's like the
past the present the future you know the
three
areas that we know about they're all
generative so there is reception of
signals
but also like all of those are
generative and then you pointed to like
this idea of kind of a cognitive degree
of freedom
in our narrative
and so we might even model that as like
an action or a movement in a narrative
space
and so
how
do we make appropriate actions in
narrative space because do we just say
okay graduate student no
they're awesome
or how do we know
what to say and how to actually
yeah so so this is a student of mine
that i mentioned this patient of mine
who happens to be a graduate student so
he's about to you know finish up and go
on to a postdoc and i actually suggested
that to him as sort of a as an
experiment right because i often talk
about this as an experiment i said you
know as you move on to your next lab why
don't you try an experiment where you
just
take as
like an a priori supposition that
everybody in the lab loves you
that that that they want the best for
you that they are your friends
and anytime you have like a paranoid
thought or a negative thought about them
really critically appraise that and
really even doubt that and fact check it
or reality test it with somebody else
that you know
and i think through that he might be
able through iterative processes because
it's such a feed-forward cycle the
problem is when we're paranoid or
suspicious of other people they sense it
and they weigh back off and then as soon
as they back off we get more paranoid as
we should because they've given us the
signal that they've backed up and then
that you know it's a reinforcing cycle
so if we kind of discard that primary
narrative and then act in the world as
if right
not and not in a fake way but as if
certain things were true that we didn't
necessarily believe up front and i have
to ask my patients to do this all the
time especially when my patients who are
addicted
and whose lives are being destroyed by
their addiction
i say to them you have to imagine and
essentially have faith
that
giving up your drug of choice will lead
to a better life
right now what you see is two choices
you see continuing to use and
or stop using and being miserable and
i'm holding out to you the possibility
of stop using and being
happy or being happier than you are
while you're using but it is a leap of
faith
because you have to are going to have to
wait a long time and do a lot of things
where really you don't feel that at all
you just have to believe that it's true
and approach every day as if that is
true
the other thing i talk about in my book
which is maybe a little bit of a paradox
given what i just said is this idea of
radical honesty and how important
truth-telling is to this process again
because truth-telling is important to
build true narratives and true
narratives are important to be able to
know how to make decisions going forward
in our lives
and it's a small thing but you know my
patients will say and patients in
recovery will say i can't lie about
anything when i was using i of course
lied about my drug use but i also lied
about stuff that it didn't even matter
and my favorite anecdote is my patient
who's now in really sustained recovery
doing great he says you know when i was
using i was in the lying habit if i was
at mcdonald's and a patient called and
said hey where are you i'd say hey i'm a
burger king if i was a bird king my
patient my friend would call it say yeah
i'm in mcdonald's so it got to be like
this work like like lies about
everything so part of his recovery and
this is what i actually prescribe to
patients is radical truth telling like
you cannot tell a lie about anything
because that telling the truth i think
helps us
first of all it's it's cognitively
effortful but secondly it really grounds
us in what is true and real and helps us
in an iterative fashion stay closer to
that to build these truthful narratives
which i think are really important so
there's a bit of a paradox there because
i'm saying on the one hand
pretend stuff that you don't feel is
true
but which might be true which you can't
see but at the same time be really
honest about like your daily actions
nice here here were some of the active
themes that i kind of heard there
action as a self-fulfilling prophecy and
action as being in the business of
acquiring evidence for a given
generative model that's a big theme and
also in order to switch action policies
there has to be
a transient suppression of precision on
the policy like if we're sitting down we
have to transiently
implicitly or explicitly believe that it
could be a different way otherwise we'll
just continue to get evidence that we're
sitting down
and then
um it's a very
active way to kind of escape that
gaslight paradox
so
you were talking about setting a
confident prior for the next epoch
and so that just
today you're low on how you believe
others think of you and uncertain or
you're low and precise but great it's
actually all in the past now
behaviorally and then in your next
endeavor
you could just try
starting higher in an unknown future but
just peg it
higher and try to be more precise which
is going to look like
being more skeptical looking for
evidence on the upside
and so it's like
instead of focusing on the past and
trying to re-narrativize the past
we can include the behavior of the past
which for sure is inalterable
into a prospective narrative of the
future that makes actions like patience
maybe
more plausible
yeah love it um i mean dislikes love
that science speak it's so exciting and
it maps so well to like you know these
kinds of aphorisms
or sort of
the approach that we take in psychiatry
and psychotherapy using very different
language and that's always really
exciting and it just reminds me so much
of
you know the alcoholics anonymous saying
of taking it one day at a time which is
so fundamental for this whole process
because what happens when we take it one
day at a time it means that we wake up
and we say the past is the past
the future is the future
all i need to do today
is focus on what i can do today
to make my life
and your life and our lives a little bit
better without putting too heavy on me
like i mean i'm not going to go and like
save people in ukraine obviously but
what are the things that i can do i can
pick up that piece of garbage so it kind
of narrows the time scope it forces us
to be in the here and now which also
expands our senses so that we can take
in more actual data so that i'm not like
ruminating and cogitating on my own you
know sort of self-involved you know
problems which is where
like you know most of us spend a lot of
our headspace i don't know why we do
that but we do but instead i noticed
that there's like a reese's peanut
butter cup wrapper on the ground i could
pick that up right that's one thing that
or i i could notice that i have the urge
to lie about why i'm late for this
meeting
but i could not i could choose not to do
that i can choose that today that's kind
of exciting
like to me that sort of opens up all
kinds of possibilities because i'm not
future catastrophizing i'm also not
future grandiosing you know where they
like oh i have to do this i have to do
that or i'm not going to be good enough
i'm not ruminating on my pastels i'm
saying you know what today is the only
unit of time that i really need to focus
on and a string i always say to my
patients a string of good days makes a
string of good weeks and a string of
good weeks it's a string of good months
and before you know it you've got a
couple good decades and that's a
lifetime and that's a life well lived
which is what we all want
and to even bring in one other active
term the affordance which is the
capacity for action which comes from the
ecological psychology field
the affordance is relational and so it's
about like the motivation by that entity
and the agency that they feel they do or
don't have from a narrative perspective
and the affordances that the niche
scaffolds and provides for them or not
and also the narratives that the niche
provides or not and then like that
is what is going to be engaged in that
behavioral decision in the moment and
then you also talk about like adding
friction as like a pragmatic strategy
that i'm sure everyone has experimented
with variously on different
facets but it's like it's an example
about
the pragmatic
tips
but also they're connected to behavioral
and cognitive modeling
in this
perhaps even formal way
yeah
exactly
um well
we covered many fun topics like just a
few that i kind of wrote down where
patients
i guess the patients who you clinically
see and having patience in the moment
and then
uh expectations
action
and taking action as a first
perturbation then the dopamine as reward
and
epistemic and pragmatic value and
there's a lot of interesting research on
active inference and dopamine signaling
and then a lot of active terms like
action priors confidence precision
narrative information
like all the amazing terms and just very
fun and also powerful book and a lot of
great material
thank you daniel this has been
really fun as i knew it would be as
talking to you is always
illuminating and
surprising in
fun and positive way
i always learn
then i have
so much respect for your
you know intelligence and creativity
it's always exciting
thank you and hope to talk to you and
any others from the farm in the future
sounds great
bye see ya
you